玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
ln the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence...
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
宇宙碰撞
Cosmic collisions...
它们属于宇宙间最暴戾
they are among the most violent...
最能改变生命的现象
and life-altering phenomena in the universe.
从小碰小擦到高速碰撞
From fender-benders to high-velocity impacts...
引力让宇宙万物不断运动
gravity is constantly moving everything around in space...
致使物体终将碰撞在一起
and so things are bound to collide.
小行星 慧星 星系 行星
Asteroids, comets, galaxies, and planets...
是涉及这些暴力事件的一些对象
are some of the objects involved in these energized events.
虽然 这些撞击听上去很黄很暴力
Yet as violent and destructive as these collisions sound...
但是 我们可能得将我们的存在归功于它们
we may owe ourvery existence to them.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第十二集 宇宙碰撞
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 12of19 Cosmic.Collisions
达林·拉格森正致力于搜寻
Darin Ragozzine is on the hunt for answers...
很久以前 发生在遥远太空中的一次碰撞的原因
to an ancient collision that happened far off in space.
拉格森瞄准了一块醒目的灰色石头
Ragozzine has zeroed in on a vibrant gray rock.
那是很久以前两个庞然大物
lt's the vestige of an ancient fiery impact...
猛烈碰撞的残余物
involving two massive objects...
最大的有冥王星那么大
the largest being the size of Pluto.
这块大石头名叫2003EL61
This gargantuan rock, called 2003 EL61...
是在海王星边上打转的碰撞家族的一员
is a member of a collisional family...that orbits just beyond the planet Neptune.
碰撞家族是一群天体
Collisional families are groups of objects...
具有相似的形状 尺寸
that have very similar shapes, sizes, and tilts...
它们围绕太阳旋转的倾角也相似
as they go around the Sun.
它们簇拥在轨道上
They stayed in a tight cluster of orbits...
因为它们来自同相同的物体
because they came from the same objects.
来自同一个行星的物体
Objects that came from the same parent...
应该是同样的物质构成的
should be made out of the same material.
因此 通过研究其成分以核实它们的相同之处
So, by studying the compositions and verifying that they're similar...
我们可以知道它们是同宗同祖
we can know that they came from the same origin.
数十亿年前 2003 EL61及其家人
Billions ofyears ago, 2003 EL61 and its family members...
是千里之外的一个庞大天体的组成部分
were part of one gigantic body over a thousand miles across.
庞大天体位于柯伊伯带
The mammoth object resided in the Kuiper Belt...
那是未成为行星的天体的仓库
a repository for objects that didn't become planets...
位于外太阳系
in the outer solar system.
然而那时
But at that time...
柯伊伯带挤满了自由散漫的物体
the Kuiper Belt was buzzing with loose objects.
冰覆盖的石块
The ice-covered rock...
最后撞上了其一半大小的物体
eventually slammed into another object half its size...
时速估计达到了3000英里
at a speed estimated at 3,000 miles per hour.
撞击产生的能量相当于100亿个原子弹
The impact produced energy equivalent to ten billion atomic bombs.
还从物体中弹出了大块的冰
lt also ejected large chunks of ice from the object...
每一个的范围从直径250英里
each one ranging from 250 miles in diameter...
到眼镜般大小
down to mere specks.
这些碎片现在都是碰撞家族的成员
The fragmented pieces are now all members of a collisional family...
其中2003 EL61是最大的一个
with 2003 EL61 being the largest piece.
我们现在是在陶土飞靶射击场里
We're here at a clay pigeon shooting range...
因为 陶土飞靶被击中后的碎片的弹道
because the trajectory of the shards after a clay pigeon is hit...
非常类似于那个家族成员的轨道
is very similar to the orbits that family members take.
一旦被击中则碎片飞出
Once it's hit, the pieces fly out...
但是它们在落下时几乎遵循同样的弹道
but they pretty much follow that same trajectory as they go down.
至于2003EL61
ln the case of 2003 EL61...
碰撞使它快速旋转
the impact has been sending it rapidly spinning...
犹如乘坐游戏机一般 每4小时旋转一次
like an amusement ride, rotating once every four hours.
因其遭到侧击所以不停地旋转
lt got hit sideways, and so it was spinning.
由于它旋转得非常快因而身子拉长了
And because it's spinning so fast, it elongates itself...
身子拔长了所以其形状有点像橄榄球
pulls itself out, and it's shaped sort of like a football...
无非它更像瘪了气的橄榄球
except it's more like a football where you let out some of the air...
一头有点扁
and squash it on one end.
所以 2003 EL61是太阳系里已知旋转最快的大物体
So 2003 EL61 is the fastest-spinning large object that we know...
还没有类似的物体
anywhere in the solar system.
行星天文学家迈克·布朗
Planetary astronomer Mike Brown...
对2003EL61这个柯伊伯带中最大最亮的物体
has conducted extensive surveying of 2003 EL61...
进行了广泛的勘察
the biggest and brightest known object in the Kuiper Belt.
它很亮很大 但又闪闪发光
lt's bright, it's big, but it's also very shiny...
因为 我们认为在碰撞发生时
because we think when the collision happened...
其周围的大部分冰挪开了
most of that ice got removed and the things around it.
只留下了一点薄薄的一层纯冰
And it just left a little, thin layer...
在这石块的顶部
of almost pure ice sitting on top of this rock.
那就是为何它要比其它物体看上去更加闪亮
And that's why it's so much shinier...than everything else we see up there.
就在于上头有纯冰
lt's that pure ice that's out there.
我认为 2003EL61 是那里最大的物体
l think that 2003 EL61 is the largest object out there...
是碰撞产生了一个家族
that had a collision that formed a family.
我确实认为那是太阳系史上
l really do think it's one of the largest collisions...
发生在太阳系外部的
that occurred in the outer part of the solar system...
最大的碰撞之一
in the history of the solar system.
碰撞不仅创造了2003EL61
The impact not only created 2003 EL61...
及其星系家族 同时也产生了两颗卫星
and its galactic family, it also produced two moons.
我们现在在搜寻它们
We're searching for them now...
就是柯伊伯带里拥有卫星的10%的物体
and something like ten percent of Kuiper Belt objects have moons.
然而 我们见到过的所有这些物体
But all of these objects that we've looked at...
只有少量拥有的卫星超过一个
only a few have more than one moon.
红外线望远镜通过测量其发热
lnfrared telescopes determine the size of these objects...
来测定这些物体的个头
by measuring the heat they emit.
尽管 2003EL61有100倍于其家族的第二大成员
Although 2003 EL61 is a hundred times larger...than its next biggest family member...
但是 这个支离破碎的群体依然保持着同样的轨道
this fragmented group maintains similar orbits.
这些碎片呆在一起 在围绕太阳的轨道上
The pieces stay together and keep following each other...
保持着相互之间的队形
in their orbits around the Sun.
因而 天文学家可以通过观察共同的轨道特征
So astronomers can identify collisional families...
来甄别碰撞家族
by looking for common orbital characteristics.
所以 与太阳的距离决定了轨道的形状
So, the distance from the Sun, how elliptical the orbit is.
你扣发猎枪的扳机 射出的霰弹
When you shoot a shotgun, the pellets go out...
就会进入散开前的子弹一样的弹道
into similar trajectories as the original object.
同样太阳系里的碰撞家族
This is the same as in collisional families...
碰撞后的轨道会遵循原来物体的轨道
which follow similar orbits after the collision...in the solar system...as the original object was under.
这就是 我们能够甄别他们的道理
And this is how we're able to identify them.
所以在碰撞发生后 它们都处于少有不同的轨道上
So after this collision happens, they are on slightly different orbits.
就像跑道上的运动员 如果他们都是在自己的跑道上
And like runners on a track, if they all stayed in their own lanes...
如果他们奔跑的速度都一样
if they all ran about the same speed...
由于跑道的长度略有不同
because the lanes have slightly different lengths...
不一会儿若你再看跑道
after a while, if you looked at the track...
每个运动员在跑道上的位置就会有所不同了
each runnerwould be at a different place along the track.
碰撞家族成员现在的情况和这一样
And this is the same forfamily members right now.
所以即使它们现在互不挨着
So even though they're not next to each other today...
但我们观察它们时依然能甄别出来
when we look at them, we can still identify each
根据它们运行方式
in terms of the way their orbits are...
它们围绕太阳的运行方式
the way they go around the Sun.
科学家在揣摩2003EL61是否
Scientists wonder whether 2003 EL61...
最终会卷入另一次碰撞
could eventually be involved in another collision.
貌似海王星的引力在拽着它
lt seems as though Neptune is gravitationally tugging on it...
最终会改变它的轨道
which will eventually change its orbit.
在1亿年里
ln a hundred million years...
它几乎不会穿越海王星的轨道
it's going tojust barely cross the orbit of Neptune.
在这一点上很难预料接下来发生的事情
At that point, it's hard to guess what's going to happen.
海王星要么将它抛进太阳系
Neptune can either throw it into the inner solar system...
要么将它甩掉
or it can try to toss it out...
要么还有其他情况发生
or many different things can happen.
物体会定期闯出柯伊伯带
Objects are periodically bumped out of the Kuiper Belt...
往太阳系内部游荡而来
and drif t in the direction of the inner solar system.
这些冰石变成彗星
These icy rocks become comets...
拖着长长的冰尘尾巴
as they form long tails of ice and dust...
朝太阳奔来
when moving towards our Sun.
最后 它对准的目标或许是木星
Eventually, it will work its way perhaps to Jupiter.
此时 木星其实会将它抛出太阳系
At that point, Jupiter actually throws it out of the solar system.
如果2003EL61那样大小的东西撞击木星
No one has really thought about what would happen...
没有人能想到其结果的
if something the size of 2003 EL61 hit Jupiter.
然而 已知有较小的彗星打击过这颗气体巨星了
But smaller comets have been known to strike the gas giant.
1994年7月 哈勃太空望远镜
ln July1994, the Hubble Space Telescope...
观察到了一次惊人的事件
observed an astonishing event.
一连串的彗星碎片 叫做舒梅克·列维彗星9
A string of comet fragments, called Shoemaker-Levy 9...
以时速13万英里撞上木星
crashed into Jupiter at the speed of130,000 miles per hour.
最大的彗星碎片
The largest cometary piece...
释放了600万兆顿的当量
released six million megatons of explosive energy.
它们撞击木星 每7小时约20次
They impacted Jupiter about twenty times every seven hours...
直到自我毁灭
until they were destroyed.
撞击点在木星表面留下了疤痕
The points of impact left scars on the surface of Jupiter...
暴力事件的提示
reminders of the violent event.
喷气推进实验室资深科学家唐·约曼斯
JPL senior scientist Don Yeomans...
分析了舒梅克·列维彗星9事件
has analyzed the Shoemaker-Levy 9 event.
舒梅克·列维彗星9撞击
The Shoemaker-Levy 9 impacts...
让公众和科学界大开眼界
was an eye-openerfor the public and the scientific community...
在这个意义上这些宇宙撞击
in the sense that these cosmic collisions...
是偶尔发生的
do happen from time to time...
它们产生的能量实在惊人
and the energy that they could generate arejust enormous.
幸运的是 这玩艺打击的是木星而不是地球
lt's a good thing this thing hit Jupiter and not the Earth...
因为会在地球上造成严重的后果
'cause there would've been a serious problem on Earth.
要是舒梅克·列维彗星9撞击地球
Had the Shoemaker-Levy 9 struck Earth...
就会产生破坏性的陨石坑
it would have made devastating impact craters...
最大的会有40英里宽
the largest about forty miles wide.
其中任何一个都会毁灭一座大都会
Any one of them could have destroyed a metropolitan city...
激起的尘埃足以遮挡阳光数个月
and churned up enough dust to block sunlight for months.
木星位于外太阳系
Jupiter, being in the outer solar system...
其质量远远超过了所有其它行星加在一起
and being far more massive than any of the other planets combined...
遭遇了大量有可能光顾地球的打击
takes a lot of hits that might have otherwise been destined for Earth.
所以说 木星大哥在那里关注着我们
So big brother Jupiter is out there watching us.
木星就像是星际守门员
Jupiter acts like a planetary goalkeeper...
然而 要是2003EL61挣脱了柯伊伯带
but will it be able to deflect 2003 EL61...
朝地球一路翻滚而来的话
if it breaks loose from the Kuiper Belt...
木星会偏离它吗？
and tumbles toward Earth?
有可能会像舒梅克·列维彗星9那样
lt's also possible that it could hit Jupiter...
击中木星
like Shoemaker-Levy 9 did.
这个物体2000倍于击中木星的东西
This object is about 2,000 times bigger...
舒梅克·列维彗星9
than the thing that hit Jupiter, than Shoemaker-Levy 9.
所以 那将会是夜空中一次不可思议的爆炸
So it would be an incredible explosion in the night sky.
将会是你见到的一次最难以忘怀的事情
lt would be the single most prominent thing that you could see.
其尾巴至少会大于满月
lt would be bigger than the full Moon...at least the tail of it.
因为碰撞家族难以定位
Because collisional families are difficult to locate...
所以研究人员正竭力研究2003EL61及其家属
researchers are eager to study 2003 EL61 and its relatives.
对于柯伊伯带里的碰撞家族知之甚少
Less is known about collisional families in the Kuiper Belt...
只是因为对柯伊伯带成员的了解要少于
simply because fewer Kuiper Belt members are known...
我们对小行星的了解
than we know about asteroids.
所以对于发现柯伊伯带里的碰撞家族
So less research has been done to try to find collisional families...
很少有过研究
within the Kuiper Belt.
截至今日 我们只知道柯伊伯带里的这一个碰撞家族
As of today, we know of only this one collisional family in the Kuiper Belt.
它们很难发现和识别
They're very hard to find and to recognize.
我们非常幸运有了2003EL61及其家族
And we got extremely lucky with 2003 EL61 and its family.
我们现在正致力于
We're working right now...
努力找到其它的手段来发现
trying to figure out otherways that we might be able to find...
其它的家族 因为它们一定在那里 -
these additional families, 'cause they must be there...
然而我们就是不知道如何去发现它们
but wejust don't know how to find them yet.
犹如这些陶土飞靶碎片
Like these clay pigeon pieces...
2003EL61的家族成员
family members from the 2003 EL61 family...
如今都逗留在相同的轨道上
all remain in similar orbits today.
我们现在能够跟踪它们
We're able to follow them today...
更多地了解柯伊伯带及其碰撞的历史
and to learn more about the history...of the Kuiper Belt and of collisions.
一个永恒之谜
One enduring mystery...
就是2003EL61发生碰撞的时间
is when the 2003 EL61 collision actually occurred.
我们认为 我们现在可以看到各个物体所处的位置
We think we can look at where the different objects are now...
尝试让时间倒流
and try to essentially run time backwards...
来计算出那次大碰撞的时间
and figure out when they were in this one big collision.
我们最大的估计就是答案基本上是
Our best guess is that that answer is going to be essentially...
在太阳系的诞生时
at the very beginning of the solar system.
2003 EL61及其家族或许诞生于
2003 EL61 and its family were probably created...
太阳系历史上一个最混乱的时期
during one of the most turbulent periods...in the history of our solar system...
当时碰撞如夜空中的星星那样常见
when collisions were as common as stars in the night sky.
从一开始碰撞就一直是不争的事实
From the beginning, collisions have been a fact of life in space.
它们打造了我们宇宙的大部分 与此同时
They created much of our universe, and at the same time...
又一路毁灭了部分
destroyed some of it along the way.
碰撞是构建行星的手段
Collisions are the way that you build planets.
没有碰撞就没有行星的诞生
Without collisions, you don't have planets to begin with.
始于很小的粒子
You start out with very small particles...
相互之间碰撞在一起
each one of them collides together...
越来越大 越来越大
bigger and bigger and bigger and bigger...
一直到慢慢地打造出这些行星
until you slowly build up these planets.
同时碰撞也能够毁灭行星
At the same time, collisions can destroy planets.
我们太阳系里的行星
The planets in our solar system...
诞生于所谓的密集轰炸时期
were created during a period called the heavy bombardment...
那是45亿年前的事
that happened over 4.5 billion years ago.
碰撞没有随着密集轰炸而告结束
And the collisions didn't stop with the heavy bombardment.
6亿年后
Over 600 million years later...
我们太阳系又经历了另一次碰撞的打击
our solar system experienced another spike in collisions...
那是所谓的后密集轰炸时期
during a period called the late heavy bombardment.
零散的石块太小不足以成为行星
Stray rocks, too small to become planets...
玩起了星际台球
played interplanetary billiards...
大力击打和弹开其他物体
striking and bouncing off other bodies...with tremendous force.
大量物体四处飘荡
There were chunks of things flying everywhere...
以致无数的碰撞
and so there were many, many, many collisions.
你见到的月球上的大量陨石坑
A lot of the craters that you see on the Moon...
就是形成于那次非常早期
were from that very early period...
就是太阳系还在形成的时期
right when the solar system was still forming.
我们的月球揭示了当时的地球有多动荡
And our Moon reveals just howvolatile the period was on Earth.
我们甚至可以基于月球的创伤
We can even calculate to some degree...
计算出其中的程度
based on cratering on the Moon...
就是我们遭受打击的这些相当大的物体
just how often we got hit by these rather large objects...
会有6英里宽
say, six miles across.
后密集轰炸时期临近结束时
Towards the end of the late heavy bombardment...
我们看到有数百英里直径的小行星
we do get asteroids hundreds of miles in diameter...
前来攻击地球
coming in and striking the planet.
它们肯定会蒸发海洋
Those are certainly capable ofvaporizing the oceans...
在打击的地方留下疤痕
and leaving a tremendous scar where they hit...
提升表面环境
raising the surface environment...
远超出生命生存的可能
far beyond the possibility of any life surviving.
约38亿年前 后密集轰炸时期尘埃落定后
When the late heavy bombardment subsided...approximately 3.8 billion years ago...
没有凝结成行星的物体
objects that didn't coagulate into planets...
在宇宙坟场找到了安身之处
sought refuge in cosmic graveyards.
在外太阳系
ln the outer solar system...
剩余的石块就栖息在了柯伊伯带
leftover rocks reside in the Kuiper Belt.
在太阳系内部
ln the inner solar system...
它们聚集到了小行星带的轨道上
they collectively orbit in the asteroid belt.
就像在柯伊伯带里
Like in the Kuiper belt...
碰撞家族也已经在小行星带里发现
collisional families have also been discovered in the asteroid belt.
它们是小行星碎片
They're pieces of asteroids that originated from a larger object...
源自一颗大行星与另一颗小行星碰撞的碎片
that was broken apart by a collision with another asteroid.
小行星带里的碰撞家族
Collisional families in the asteroid belt...
导致了一颗小行星遭遇另一颗小行星时
result when one asteroid gets hit by another...
劈裂成碎片
and breaks into pieces.
碎片实际上会绕太阳的轨道上粘在一起
The fragments actually stick together...
天文学家可以认出这些碰撞家族
And astronomers can identify collisional families...in their orbit around the Sun.
通过观察它们与太阳的距离是否相同
by looking if their distance from the Sun is the same...
其轨道倾角是否相同
the tilt of their orbit is the same...
还有其轨道的椭圆率 扁的程度是否相似
and the ellipticity, how squashy the orbit is, is similar.
同时 如果我们看到小行星的成分相同
Also, if we see that the asteroids...are made out of the same material...
那极有可能它们是源自同一个物体
it's a good bet that they may have originated from the same object.
在小行星带里 有大约20 30个碰撞家族
There are approximately twenty to thirty known collisional families...in the asteroid belt.
科学家对产生 Baptistina 家族的
Scientists are keenly interested in one galactic collision...
星际碰撞极感兴趣
that produced the Baptistina family...
其飘忽不定的碎片源自
wayward fragments that originated as one single body...
一个大小如珠穆朗玛峰的物体
the size of Mount Everest.
约1.6亿年前 这块巨石
About160 million years ago, this colossal rock...
遭到了小行星带里的另一块巨石的侧击
was broadsided by another giant rock in the asteroid belt.
极度撞击产生了大量的小碎片
The deep impact created a shower of smaller pieces...
超过了13.6万个
over136,000 of them.
科学家估计有两成的石头
Scientists estimate that twenty percent of the rocks...
逃离了小行星带
escaped the asteroid belt...
其中有2%落到了地球
and two percent of them rained down on Earth.
有人称有九成的可能性
Some say there's a ninety percent probability...
一颗Baptistina小行星
that one of the Baptistina asteroids...
要对恐龙的灭绝负责
was responsible for the extinction of the dinosaur.
6500万年前
Sixty-five million years ago...
大量恐龙物种统治着史前世界
a myriad of dinosaur species ruled the prehistoric world...
然而 灾难事件将它们从地球的表面抹去了
but a catastrophic event wiped them off the face of the Earth.
现在科学家对它们的遭遇有了很好的证据
Now scientists have good evidence ofwhat happened to them.
现在已经证明 有一个庞大的宇宙物体
lt's now been confirmed that a gargantuan cosmic object...
从天而降
plummeted down from the sky...
在尤卡坦半岛爆炸
and exploded in the Yucatan Peninsula...
就在现在的墨西哥奇克苏卢布村庄附近
near the modern-day Mexican village of Chicxulub.
我们认为 那是个直径6英里的物体
We think it was an object about six miles in diameter...
时速约12英里
coming in at about twelve miles per second...
产生了约6500万兆吨的TNT当量的冲击能
which would cause an impact energy...of about 65 million megatons of TNT.
平心而论
Now, to put that in perspective...
那相当于140年里每秒钟发生一次广岛爆炸
that's about one Hiroshima-type blast...every second for about140 years.
那实在是个地狱般的状况
lt was really quite a hellish environment.
据信这颗小行星造成了当时地球上的
lt's believed that this asteroid contributed to the mass extinction...
75%的物种的大量灭绝
of over seventy-five percent of the species on Earth at the time.
我们认为奇克苏卢布撞击带来的后果
What we think happened with the Chicxulub impact...
就是会有较大的小行星闯入打击地球
is you have a large asteroid coming in, it hits the Earth...
会将大量的碎片和尘埃抛进大气层
it throws an enormous cloud of debris and dust into the atmosphere.
它实际上遮蔽了大部分阳光
This effectively screened out a large fraction of the Sunlight.
难以想象连续多年的不见天日
So imagine a cloudy day that lasts for years.
艾米·迈因策尔通过参观加州长滩的太平洋水族馆
Amy Mainzer has investigated the rapid die-off of life...as a result of the impact...
调查了由那次撞击造成的生命快速死亡
by visiting the Aquarium of the Pacific...in Long Beach, Calif ornia.
我们可以通过观察这个漂亮的水槽
We can learn about the effects that an asteroid impact...
来认识小行星撞击对地球可能会造成的影响
might have had on planet Earth by looking at this nice tank here.
我们看到这里充满了多姿多彩的生命
We see that it's full of color and life...
大量的各种物种 各种动植物
lots of different species, many different animals and plants.
当然 这整个生态系统最终都依赖太阳
Of course, this whole ecosystem depends ultimately on the Sun.
大鱼 如我们所见 吃小鱼
Big fish, like we see here, eat the littler fish.
小鱼吃水草
The little fish eat the plants.
最后植物靠阳光产生能量
And, ultimately, the plants depend on sunlight to make energy...
这个过程叫做光合作用
through a process called photosynthesis.
所以 你可以想象出要是发生有什么遮蔽阳光
So you can imagine that if something happens...that screens out the sunlight...
那么 所有这些漂亮的动物将通通完蛋
all these beautiful animals will perish.
这个启示录事件被称为K-T灭绝事件
The apocalyptic event has been called the K-T extinction...
源自一层地质带的签名
because of a thin band of geological signatures...
那期间 整个世界都处于
dating to that time, all over the world...
所谓的白垩纪-第三纪 即K-T界面上
known as the Cretaceous-Tertiary, or K-T boundary.
它分为爬行动物时期和哺乳动物时期
lt separates the age of reptiles and the age of mammals.
K-T界面以下没发现过恐龙的遗骨
Dinosaur bones are not found below the K-T boundary.
有人称那就是一个很好的标记
Some say it's a good indicator...
它们及其它物种的灭绝是
that they and other species became extinct...
由于多年阳光被遮蔽的影响
from the impact that blocked out sunlight foryears.
我们通过深水和浅水海洋系统的比较
We can get an idea...ofwhat might have happened to life on planet Earth...
可以得到一个概念即地球生命在
following an asteroid impact...
那颗小行星撞击后可能会产生的影响
by comparing deep-water and shallow-water marine systems.
在深水区由于阳光较少
ln deeperwater, where there's less sunlight...
就鲜有色彩斑斓的珊瑚和鱼类
there are fewer colorful corals, fewer types of colorful fish...
总体上物种的多样性较少
and generally less species diversity overall.
有些科学家一直怀疑
Some scientists had been skeptical...
是小行星造成了K-T灭绝
that an asteroid caused the K-T extinction.
长期以来人们确实不相信
For a long time, people didn't really start to believe...
小行星真的撞击了地球
that asteroids could really hit the Earth...
留下了明显的痕迹
and make a noticeable impression...
直到流星陨石坑的发现
until the discovery of Meteor Crater.
近5万年前 更新世时期
Almost 50,000 years ago, during the Pleistocene period...
一颗150英尺的小行星撞击了地球
a 150-foot asteroid struck Earth...
裹挟着2.5兆顿当量的力道
with the force of 2.5 megatons of TNT.
那次撞击掀掉了1.75万吨的岩石
The impact carved out 175 million tons of rock...
就在现在的亚利桑那沙漠里
in what is now the Arizona desert.
留下了一个巨大的碗状大坑
lt left a giant bowl-shaped hole...
被命名为流星陨石坑
which has been named Meteor Crater.
事实上 证据表明 那必定是源自小行星的撞击
ln fact, evidence proved that it had to have resulted...from an asteroid impact.
一位名叫尤金·舒梅克的科学家
A scientist named Eugene Shoemaker...
在坑底发现了冲击石英
found shocked quartz at the bottom of the crater...
这种特殊的玻璃只能产生于
and it's only possible to get this particular kind of glass...
极短的时间内产生的极端高温高压中
with extremely high temperatures and pressures...generated in a very short amount of time.
到了1980年代 科学家还没有找到
By the1980s, scientists hadn't found an impact crater...
与K-T灭绝有关的撞击坑
linked to the K-T extinction...
但是他们挖到了其他证据
but they had dug up other evidence.
从K-T界面获得了铱
lridium was procured from the K-T boundary layer.
铱是一种地球岩石中罕见的元素
lridium is an element rare in rocks on Earth...
然而在许多小行星上很普遍
but common in many asteroids.
原来有些小行星富含铱
lt turns out that some asteroids...are very high in iridium...
因此它们使得这层6500万年前
so they made the connection that this layer of iridium...
沉淀物里的铱联系上了
that occurred in a sediment layer some sixty-five million years ago...
一颗闯入的小行星
was due to an incoming asteroid.
即使发现了铱
Even with the discovery of iridium...
但还是有人质疑是小行星造成了K-T灭绝
some still doubted an asteroid caused the K-T extinction...
直到1990年代
until the 1990s...
墨西哥石油公司发现了真凭实据
when a Mexican oil company found the smoking gun.
在尤卡坦半岛外钻井时
While drilling off the Yucatan Peninsula...
他们发现了100英里宽的撞击坑
they discovered a hundred-mile-wide impact crater...
埋藏于水下3000英尺的石灰岩里
buried underwater beneath 3,000 feet of limestone.
岩石分析证明
Analysis of the rock confirmed...
那事实上是小行星形成的陨石坑
that the craterwas, in fact, formed by an asteroid.
和亚利桑那的流星陨石坑一样
And like Meteor Crater in Arizona...
在K-T撞击坑里 也发现了冲击石英即玻璃
shocked quartz or glass was also discovered...at the K-T impact crater site.
奇克苏卢布撞击的另一个有关证据是
One of the other important lines of evidence...
发现了冲击石英
for the impact at Chicxulub was the finding of shocked glass.
基本上 他们观察撞击点及其周边地区时
Basically, when they looked at the impact site...
以及世界各地 事实上
and in regions around it...
找到的玻璃都是烧结的
and all around the world, in fact...
基本上都是大爆炸熔化烧结的
lt was basically created when the giant explosion fused it.
这种特殊的玻璃形式
And this particular glass type is really only found...
只能在巨大的爆炸状态下产生
in the presence of an extremely large explosion.
如今 许多科学家都同意了
Today, many scientists agree...
是小行星造成了6500万年前的K-T灭绝
an asteroid caused the K-T extinction...sixty-five million years ago.
现在有人试图找出造成那次事件的具体那颗小行星
And now some are trying to zero in...on the exact asteroid that caused the event.
奇克苏卢布获得的沉淀物
Sediments procured from the Chicxulub site...
表明那个小行星是碳粒陨星
reveal the asteroid was a carbonaceous chondrite...
一块非常原始的石头
a very primitive rock.
这类石头的成分类似于Baptistina 家族
These types of rocks have similar compositions...
一堆小行星都起源于同一块大石头
to the Baptistina family, a collection of asteroids...that once originated from a larger rock.
所以 有人称Baptistina家族成员
So some say the odds are great...
引发了彻底消灭了恐龙的大灭绝的
that a Baptistina family member...
可能性非常大
triggered the mass extinction that wiped out the dinosaur.
现在Baptistina家族依然构成着威胁
Today, the Baptistina family could still pose a threat.
在小行星带里 其家属跨越的区域
Within the asteroid belt, its relatives span a region...
包括了两个引力舱口
containing two gravitational hatches.
这个区域 只要轻轻一推
These are areas where a slight nudge...
就能将小行星踢出轨道
could boot an asteroid out of its orbital zone.
就会游荡进太阳系内部
lt could send it soaring into the inner solar system...
就有可能撞上地球
where it could slam into planet Earth.
宇宙碰撞并非过去的事情
Cosmic collisions are not a thing of the past.
它们是现行的 潜在致命的
They're ongoing and potentially deadly.
在木星和火星之间的小行星带里
Within the asteroid belt between planets Jupiter and Mars...
居住着Baptistina家族
lives the Baptistina family...
一群石头 源自一个因碰撞而粉碎的大物体
a group of rocks that originated from a larger body...that was shattered due to a collision.
碰撞后 有些Baptistina家族成员
After the impact, some Baptistina family members...
被弹出了小行星带
were ejected from the asteroid belt.
据信在6500万年前至少最后一次
lt's believed that at least one eventually struck Earth...
击中了地球
65 million years ago...
造成了恐龙的大灭绝
and caused the mass extinction of the dinosaur.
K-T灭绝事件
And the K-T extinction event...
不会是Baptistina家族狂怒的终结
may not be the end of the Baptistina family's wrath.
有人称其另一个成员
Some say another relative...
在将来会再次威胁到我们的地球
could threaten our planet again in the future.
一直存在这种可能就是Baptistina家族的另一个成员
lt's always possible that another member of the Baptistina family...
会闯入太阳系内部去撞击地球
could make its way into the inner solar system...and hit the Earth.
研究人员一直在留意Baptistina家族
Researchers have been observing the Baptistina family.
他们发现其家人拥有相似的轨道
They've discovered that its relatives share similar orbits.
但随着时间的推移-热效应:即雅科夫斯基力
But over time, a thermal effect, called the Yarkovsky force...
正将它们推入危险地带
is moving them into a danger zone.
雅科夫斯基力是作用于小行星的热效应
The Yarkovsky force is a thermal effect on asteroids...
能够改变其轨道
that has the ability to alter their orbits.
它们在阳光的照射下
When they get hit with sunlight...
需要有一点时间来加热
it takes a little while for the asteroid to heat up.
这就导致了热辐射
This results in a thermal radiation...
给小行星一点推力 改变其轨道
that gives the asteroid a little push, which changes its orbit.
雅科夫斯基力并不大
The Yarkovsky force is not very big...
但是 经过数百万年 累计就很可观了
but over millions ofyears, it adds up.
随着时间的推移 这种逐步的轨道变化
Over time, this gradual orbital shif ting...
会产生另一场巨大的影响
could produce another cataclysmic impact.
模拟表明当这些Baptistina家族成员
Simulations have been done...to show that when these Baptistina family members...
刚好与木星发生共振时
happen to get into a resonance with the planet Jupiter...
也就是说共振的发生是:
in otherwords, a resonance...
木星每转2圈时小行星会转上7圈
where the asteroid orbits seven times...for every two orbits of Jupiter...
就会碰到一个特殊的时刻
when that special moment happens...
小行星会被击向太阳系内部
the asteroids can get shot into the inner solar system...
就像是在击打弹球台上的挡板
just like hitting a flipper on a pinball machine.
部分小行星将会进入与地球交叉的轨道
Some fraction of those asteroids...are going to get into Earth-crossing orbits...
这就意味着它们有机会撞击到地球了
which means they have a chance of hitting the Earth.
如果 撞击事件发生在现在的地球任何一个地方
If an impact event happened anywhere on planet Earth today...
那就会毁灭那里的文明了
it would destroy civilization itself.
即使 你设法躲得远远的
Even if you managed to survive in a remote place...
你也极有可能会饿死
you would most likely starve.
人类有可能生存在少数地方 重新殖民
Humans would probably survive in a few places and re-colonize...
但是文明却垮掉了
but civilization would collapse.
这是扼杀文明的事件
These are civilization-killing events.
未来的碰撞可能会危及地球生命
Future collisions could be hazardous to life on Earth.
然而奇科苏卢布撞击对人类进化
But the Chicxulub impact was a fortuitous moment...
是个千载难逢的机会
for the evolution of humans.
科学家路安·贝克一辈子都在
Research scientist Luann Becker has spent her career...
调查大灭绝事件
investigating mass extinction events.
人们说要是恐龙没有灭绝的话
People say that if the dinosaurs had not perished...
人类就不可能出现
then there would be no people.
哺乳动物就不会登台
Mammals would not have taken over...
只要恐龙足够幸运
if the dinosaurs had been so fortunate...
就能够继续它们在地球上1.35亿-1.4亿年的统治
to have been able to continue to reign...beyond the 135, 40 million years...that they happened to be on the Earth.
贝克声称和人类一样恐龙在经历了
Becker claims, like humans, dinosaurs also evolved...after an epic extinction event...
地球史上最大的大灭绝事件后也进化了
the largest in the history of planet Earth.
那就是二叠纪 - 三叠纪大灭绝 也称为大灭绝事件
lt's the Permian-Triassic extinction, also known as the Great Dying.
那对我也有点讽刺的味道
lt's also kind of ironic to me...
假如我们关于二叠纪的理论是对的话
that if our theory is correct about the Permian...
即恐龙来自撞击事件
the dinosaur came in with an impact event...
消失也是因为撞击事件
and went out with an impact event...
那么那可是相当有趣的
which is pretty interesting.
这或许是终极宇宙悬案
lt's perhaps the ultimate cosmic cold case...
宇宙史上绝无仅有的大灭绝
a mass extinction unmatched in the history of the universe.
2.5亿年前
Two hundred and fif ty million years ago...
也就是恐龙称霸很久以前
long before the dinosaur ruled...
小生物以及大量的植物
smaller creatures and abundant plant life...
在二叠纪到三叠纪的地球上大量繁衍
prospered on Earth during the Permian-Triassic period.
然后某些神秘事件几乎抹掉了当时所有的生命
Then some mysterious event wiped out almost all life at that time.
事实上那是最严重的灭绝事件
ln fact, it's the most severe extinction with respect...
涉及了多少动植物的消亡
to how many different animals and plants perished.
那是我们地球生命史上最大的灭绝事件
lt's the biggest extinction event in the history of life on our planet.
贝克正着手侦破这个史前命案
Becker is on a mission to solve this prehistoric crime.
类似于涉嫌杀死恐龙的K-T 撞击
Like the K-T impact that probably killed the dinosaurs...
她声称已发现证据表明
she claims to have uncovered evidence...
有一颗巨大的小行星同样造成了二叠纪 - 三叠纪灭绝事件
that a giant asteroid also caused the Permian-Triassic extinction...
发生在1.85亿年前
which occurred about 185 million years earlier.
在二叠纪至三叠纪期间
During the Permian-Triassic period...
我们的世界由一块超级大陆 即所谓的盘古大陆
ourworld was comprised of one supercontinent called Pangaea...
以及一个超级大洋 即所谓的原始大洋构成
and a super ocean called Panthalassa.
按贝克的说法
According to Becker...
一个7英里宽的物体撞进大洋
a seven-mile-wide object slammed into the ocean...
靠近超级大陆的南端
near the southern tip of the supercontinent...
就是现在的澳大利亚的西北角外
which is now off northwestAustralia.
如果你站在2.5亿年前的海滩上
lfyou were standing on the beach 250 millions years ago...
就有可能目睹这个与众不同的事件了
you'd probably have a pretty good view of this particular event.
你会看到一个巨大的物体 珠峰一般大小
You have a large body, the size of, say, Mount Everest...
结实的身躯撞入大陆边缘
rigid body slamming into the continental margin...
就在海岸边
along the actual beach...
引发了大地震和大海啸
creating a huge earthquake, mega tsunamis...
掀起数英里尘埃直达大气层
injecting miles and miles of dust debris up into the atmosphere...
蔓延全球 遮天蔽日
distributing itself globally...in such a manner that it blocks sunlight out.
你可以看到当时有几个月暗无天日
You could have had darkness for months at a time.
这足以终止光合作用
This is enough to shut down photosynthesis.
那是食物链的顶端
That's the top of the food chain...
那就是涓滴效应
and that just has a trickle-down effect.
如果贝克的理论是正确的话
lf Becker's theory is correct...
那么这个撞击将抹去地球自结合成
this impact could have wiped out most life on Earth...
一个大陆及一个大洋以来的大部分生命
since it was concentrated on one continent and one ocean.
这种等级的灭绝事件
An extinction event of this magnitude...
将会导致完全的进化
would have allowed for complete evolutionary change...
从而为恐龙的进化扫清障碍
thus paving the way for the dinosaurs to evolve.
这只是因为
lt was only because...
二叠纪 - 三叠纪灭绝事件的发生
the Permian-Triassic extinction event occurred...
我认为恐龙得以进化某种程度上
and what l consider to be somewhat attributed...
应归因于这个撞击事件
to this impact event...that the dinosaurs were able to evolve.
二叠纪 - 三叠纪灭绝事件只留下很少的地质证据
Little geological evidence remains of the Permian-Triassic extinction.
只有极少量的2.5亿年前的岩石
There are very few 250-million-year-old rocks...
留在地球上
left on Earth...
那是因为它们随着板块构造被回收利用了
because they've been recycled by plate tectonics.
然而贝克说她在澳大利亚西北部的撞击坑
But Becker says she's found traces...
发现了踪迹
of the actual impact crater in northwestern Australia.
被称为大灭绝的二叠纪 - 三叠纪灭绝
The Permian-Triassic extinction...known as the Great Dying...
是地球史上最大的灭绝事件
was the biggest extinction event in the history of planet Earth.
2.5亿年前九成的生命消失了
Ninety percent of all life perished 250 million years ago.
期间灭绝的生命远多于
More more creatures expired during this period...
1.85亿年后灭绝恐龙的K-T 灭绝事件
than the K-T extinction that killed the dinosaurs...over185 million years later.
二叠纪 - 三叠纪灭绝的原因尚无定论
The cause of the Permian-Triassic extinction has gone unsolved.
然而现在科学家路安·贝克及其他人
But now, research scientist Luann Becker and others...
认为是小行星导致了这个事件
think an asteroid caused the event...
他们已经发现了一个潜在的撞击坑
and they've uncovered a possible impact crater...
就沉睡于澳大利亚西北部的近海里
buried under sediments offshore of northwestern Australia.
我们相信我们已经发现了那次撞击事件
We believe we found a very good candidate...
很好的候选者
forwhat is the impact event itself.
它越古老 其结构就越复杂得多
lt's much older, it's a lot more complicated...
地质过程就越漫长
and a lot more geologically processed.
它不再是完美的循环
lt's not a perfect circle anymore.
它看上去不像是靶心
lt doesn't look like a bull's-eye.
大部分二叠纪岩石已经消失了
Most of the Permian rocks have been subducted...
早就灭失 风化掉了
and they're long gone or eroded away.
那里作为撞击的证据
The evidence for an impact there...
很边缘且极具争议
is marginal and highly controversial.
有些科学家质疑
Some scientists are skeptical...
贝克发现了二叠纪 - 三叠纪年代的撞击坑
that Becker has found an impact crater...from the Permian-Triassic period.
尚未发现有合适的撞击坑能匹配二叠纪 - 三叠纪年代
No good crater has been found to match the Permian-Triassic age.
有一个主张认为澳大利亚西海岸存在一种构造
There was a claim of a structure off of the west coast ofAustralia...
但是并不明显 并不像K-T撞击那样清晰
but it's not as clean and as clear as the K-T crater.
我们没有看到确凿的证据
We don't have a smoking gun.
但是路安·贝克声称自己已经找到了确凿的证据
But Becker claims she has found the smoking gun.
此外 她和她的团队前往南极
What's more, she and her team have traveled to Antarctica...
澳大利亚 非洲 日本等地球上现存最古老岩石的地方
Australia, Africa, and Japan, where the oldest rocks on Earth exist.
他们声称已经发现了四十个撞击坑
They claim to have found forty impact tracers.
这些是地球外的矿物碎片
These are extraterrestrial mineral fragments...
发现于二叠纪 - 三叠纪年代的岩层中
recovered from rock layers...dating to the Permian-Triassic period.
我们发现了我们认为是零星的撞击碎片
We have found what we consider to be...little bits and pieces of impact debris...
这确实看上去就像是陨石那样的东西
which literally looks like what we'd find...if we were looking at a meteorite.
这有可能是一些撞击陨石碎片
lt's possible for some of the impact meteoritic debris...
落下并保存在岩层里的
to fall back down and get preserved in the rock layer.
尚未在二叠纪 - 三叠纪的岩层中发现铱
What hasn't been recovered...from the Permian-Triassic rock layer is iridium.
这种陨石物质已经帮助让许多科学家相信了
lt's the meteoritic substance...that helped to convince many scientists...
是小行星撞击造成了6500万年前的恐龙灭绝
that an asteroid impact caused the extinction of the dinosaurs...sixty-five million years ago.
同僚们试着吹毛求疵
Colleagues want to try to get real nitpicky about...
"啊 你也应该找到铱呀"
"Well, you should have found iridium, too."
我们并未在预料会发现的地方找到铱
Well, we're not finding iridium...in some of the places we would expect to find it...
比如 我们所带回的一些彗星物质中
like in some of the cometary material that we brought back.
那么那该如何解释呢？
So what's the explanation for that?
那只是物体有所不同
lt's just that there are different bodies...
它们不尽一样
and they're not all the same.
尽管贝克没有找到铱
Although Becker hasn't found iridium...
但是 她还是从南极的岩石里取得了铬
she has procured chromium in rocks from Antarctica.
和铱一样 铬也十分罕见
Like iridium, chromium is just as rare...
广泛存在于太空石头中
and is more abundant in space rocks.
那么小行星是二叠纪 - 三叠纪大灭绝的元凶
So did an asteroid actually cause...the Permian-Triassic mass extinction...
还是仅仅是帮凶呢？
or merely help it along?
看来2.5亿年前生命在顽强求生
lt appears that life was struggling to survive...250 million years ago.
地球经历着窒息着大气层的剧烈的火山活动
The planet was undergoing severe volcanism...which was choking the atmosphere.
一种可能是西伯利亚的大火山
One possibility is that a large volcano in Siberia...
它坐落在巨大的煤矿上方
which was sitting atop an enormous coal deposit...
可能向大气层排放出大量的温室气体
may have released a lot of greenhouse gases...
如二氧化碳 甲烷
into the atmosphere, such as CO2 and methane...
这会造成水生生物的大量死亡
which would cause a massive die-off among marine organisms...
同时大规模的全球变暖
and also an enormous amount of global warming...
也会危及陆生动物
which would have been bad for the terrestrial animals as well.
你要是回顾一下此类灭绝事件的关联者
When you go back and look at...what does correlate with these other extinction events...
就会发现实际上在所有的案子中
virtually in all the cases...
都同时伴随着巨大的火山喷发的证据
there's evidence of a mass volcanic episode at the same time...
所有的大灭绝事件中包括K-T灭绝
and all of the mass extinction events, including the K-T...
都紧密地联系上了这些火山喷发
are strongly and intimately associated...with these volcanic eruptions.
灭绝事件不管怎样都会发生
The extinction events may have happened anyway...
然而这颗该死的流星闯了进来
but then this damn meteor came in...
雪上加霜
and really mucked things up.
真是祸不单行
lt was a double whammy.
贝克声称光火山喷发
Becker claims that volcanism alone...
不会造成二叠纪 - 三叠纪大灭绝
couldn't have caused the Permian-Triassic extinction.
她说她有更多的证据来予以证明
And she says she has even more evidence to prove it.
我认为我们已经找到了一些最好的代用品
We have found, l think, some of the best proxies...
来作为我们的撞击示踪器
forwhat we consider to be impact tracers.
这包括了多个地方的撞击石英
This includes shocked quartz in multiple locations...
澳大利亚和南极及周边的
in and around Australia and Antarctica...
遭遇到了前所未有的压力的玻璃
glass that has seen pressures that are far beyond...
你可以考虑它会述说地球上的地质情况
what you can even think about happening...geologically speaking, on the Earth.
这不是某些火山活动所能模仿的
This could not have been mimicked...by some kind ofvolcanic event.
它必定是撞击事件所产生的东西
lt has to be something that was produced by an impact event.
我认为 一旦你有了那种直接证据
And l think that when you have that kind of direct evidence...
那实际上击中了要害
that's as good as it gets in this business.
科学界仍然在争论
The scientific community is still debating...
小行星撞击是否引发了
whether an asteroid impact helped trigger...
2.5亿年前的 二叠纪至三叠纪大灭绝
the Permian-Triassic extinction 250 million years ago.
然而 太空石头并不是会引发宇宙剧变唯一的物体
But space rocks aren't the only objects...that can cause cosmic upheaval.
事实上 我们银河系目前就陷入了
ln fact, our own Milky Way galaxy is currently involved...
一场多星系碰撞
in a multiple-galaxy collision.
想象一下 你正巡航在太空间
lmagine you're a galaxy cruising through space.
交通看似通畅 但是随时随地
The traffic may seem light, but at any moment...
你会遭遇迎面撞击
you could be involved in a head-on collision.
这样的宇宙撞击比比皆是
Cosmic crashes like this happen all the time...
尤其是星系相互之间靠得很近时
particularly when galaxies get too close to one another.
星系相互影响 有过碰撞 有过兼并
Galaxies have interacted, they've collided, they've merged...
它们有过相互撕扯
they've ripped each other apart...
现在还在进行中
and it's still going on today.
所以 星系碰撞一直是星系生命的一部分
So galactic collisions have always been a part of the life of a galaxy...
一直都是这样
and they always will be.
科学家米歇尔·泰勒
Research scientist Michelle Thaller...
知道星系碰撞会有多暴力
knows howviolent galaxy collisions can be...
尤其是 在牵涉多个星系时
especially when they involve multiple galaxies.
就在眼下 航天局的史匹哲太空望远镜
At this very moment, NASA's Spitzer Space Telescope...
正目睹着终极碰撞:
is witnessing the ultimate pile-up:
四个超大星系在宇宙高速公路上撞在了一起
Four supermassive galaxies colliding on a cosmic freeway...
距离地球约50亿光年远
approximately five billion light-years away from Earth.
它们正以时速数百万英里相互碰撞
They're all coming together now at millions of miles an hour...
它们会融合在一起
and they will merge together.
所以 我们看到了星系的惊天大碰撞
So we found an absolutely titanic collision of galaxies.
你可以将多数星系碰撞看作是
You can think of most galaxy collisions as being like...
高速公路上的小汽车的小碰小擦
you know, little compact cars maybe piling up...a small collision on a highway...
然而我们所看到的这个例子
but in this case, we're seeing maybe, you know...
就相当于四辆大型拖车迎面相撞
four eighteen-wheelers colliding together head-on...
在这过程中数十亿颗恒星
and in the process, billions of stars...
从这个星系里驱离
are being just scattered away from this galaxy.
这种暴力冲突还在不断发生
This violent collision is still happening.
碰撞最终尘埃落定后
When the impact is finally over...
这四个星系交织在一起形成一个凶残的星系
the fourwill bejumbled together to form one beastly galaxy...
是银河系的10倍
ten times the mass of our Milky Way.
将成为整个宇宙间最大的星系之一
lt will be one of the largest galaxies in the entire universe.
这只是众多多星系碰撞之一
And this is just one of many multiple-galaxy collisions.
银河系最终会与我们的邻居仙女座星系合并
The Milky Way will eventually merge...with our neighbor galaxy, Andromeda...
那会证明是一场壮观的碰撞
which could prove to be a spectacular collision.
然而 就在此时 我们银河系正与两个小星系相撞
But right now, our galaxy is actually colliding...
引发了一阵骚动
with two smaller galaxies which is causing quite a stir.
眼下有两个星系
There's two galaxies right now...
实际上是相对较小的星系
that are actually relatively small galaxies...
但是在与银河系相撞
but they're colliding with the Milky Way right now.
一个叫人马矮星系
One is called the Sagittarius dwarf...
因为 我们可以看到它坐落在人马座附近
because we see it near the constellation Sagittarius...
另一个叫大犬座矮星系
and another is called the Canis Majoris dwarf galaxy.
现在 这第二个
Now, the second one...
大犬座矮星系 非常有趣
the Canis Majoris dwarf galaxy, is very interesting...
因为它表现得有点
because it appears to have been sort of...
被拽入了银河系 并在围绕银河系中心运转时
drawn into the Milky Way and ripped apart...
被撕碎了
as it orbited around the center of the Milky Way.
所以 我们实际上看到的是星弧
So we can actually see streams of stars...
交织在一起
all going around together...
是这个可怜的小星系被撕碎后的残骸
that are the remnants of this poor little galaxy...that got ripped apart.
星系碰撞产生出数十亿颗恒星
Galaxy collisions produce billions of stars...
然而这些恒星也会碰撞吗？
but can these stars also collide?
我们银河系里恒星之间的距离非常大
The space between stars in our galaxies is absolutely huge.
如果把太阳比作篮球那么大
lf the Sun were about the size of a basketball...
在洛杉矶这里
and l'm here in Los Angeles...
那么最近的恒星
then the nearest star...
就会是在纽约那里同样大小的恒星
would be about the same-sized star in NewYork.
想象成纽约的一个篮球
lmagine a basketball in New York.
恒星之间有很大的距离
There's so much space between stars...
所以 恒星的碰撞是相当罕见的
the stellar collisions are so rare.
尽管罕见 但是星际碰撞还是会在
Although rare, star collisions can occur...
密集的星团里时有发生
where stellar objects are formed in dense clusters.
我们曾经见到过星团里的例子
We've seen examples where in a cluster of stars...
有恒星似乎天生就比其他星大很多
one star seems to be more massive than the other ones...
更加年轻 旋转也快得多
younger than the other ones, and spinning much faster...than the other stars that it was born with.
这些年轻的恒星叫做蓝离散星
These young stars are called blue stragglers.
它们所在罕见的致密星团称为球状星团
They occur in unusually dense groups of stars...called globular clusters.
它们之所以称为蓝离散星
These are called blue stragglers...
是因为它们看似较为年轻
because they seem to be younger.
它们相比星团里的其它恒星成长较慢
They're aging less quickly than the other stars of the clusters.
所以 其极有可能是 两颗恒星合并而成的
So it's very possible that these are caused...when two stars actually merge together.
在这些恒星彼此接近时
As these stars approached each other...
会通过引力相互旋转
they spun each other up with their gravity...
因此你就会看到这个快速旋转的巨大亮星
and so you get this very fast-rotating, large, bright star.
恒星碰撞绝非轻微的星际小碰小擦
And star collisions are not mild galactic fender-benders.
会具有很大的破坏性
They can be quite destructive.
它们会转得越来越靠近
They would sort of loop closer and closer together...
转得越来越快
going faster and faster.
它们的速度有可能达到时速数十万英里
They'd probably get to many hundreds of thousands...
甚至数百万英里
if not millions of miles an hour.
在它们靠得很近时会相互撕扯
And they'd begin to rip bits of each other off...as they came close to each other.
因此星际碰撞会是很有看头的
So a stellar collision could be...
极其戏剧性的暴力事件
an extremely dramatic, violent thing to watch.
最终 如果在足够的时间里有足够的物质转移
Eventually, if the mass transfer happens enough over enough time...
轨道就会收缩
the orbits will shrink...
这两颗恒星就会靠得越来越近
and those two stars will get closer and closer together...
它们最终会合并成一颗巨星
and they could eventually merge...forming either one single giant star...
或者最终塌缩成中子星 甚至黑洞
or eventually collapsing into, say, a neutron star or a black hole.
不管是恒星或星系的兼并
Whether they're star and galaxy mergers...
还是小行星或彗星的碰撞
or asteroid and comet impacts...
宇宙碰撞还会继续发生
cosmic collisions will continue to happen...
只要宇宙继续存在
as long as the universe exists.
通过这些不可抗事件的知识的逐步积累
By gaining knowledge about these uncontrollable events...
我们就可以达到更好地了解
we can reach a better understanding...
宇宙的起源或许可以预测其未来
about the origins of the universe, and possibly predict its future.
宇宙碰撞一直是塑造地球演化和历史的主要因素
Cosmic collisions have been a majorfactor...shaping the evolution and history of the planet.
没有它们就不会有地球
Earth wouldn't be here without them.
生命起源所需的化学物质
The chemicals that life needs to get started with...
也是来自这些碰撞的过程
came out as a result of these impact processes.
这其实一直是地球生命史上一个非常重要的因素
This has actually been a very important factor...in the history of life on this planet.
宇宙碰撞带来了形形色色的东西
Cosmic collisions are responsible...
如 小行星撞击
for things as varied as asteroid impacts...
星系兼并 巨星的形成
galaxy mergers, formation of giant stars.
它们显然是我们了解宇宙现象的关键
They're obviously key to our understanding...of the phenomena in the universe.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing